Finding aid for the Francesca Roccaforte papers LSC.2165
UCLA Library Special Collections
Francesca Roccaforte papers
1977-1994
UCLA Library Special Collections
Roccaforte, Francesca
LSC.2165
0.2 linear feet (1 half document box)
Francesca Roccaforte is a photographer and teacher living in San Francisco, California. This collection contains photographic prints from several of her projects ranging from documenting horse races to Italian historical sites.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Francesca Roccaforte, 2013.
This collection is part of an outreach and collection-building partnership between the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives, the UCLA Center for the Study of Women (CSW), and the UCLA Library.
Sponsor
The June L. Mazer Lesbian Archive at UCLA is an outreach and collection-building partnership between the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives, the UCLA Center for the Study of Women (CSW), and the UCLA Library. These collections expand the pool of primary source materials available to researchers and to the community at large. This partnership was initiated by CSW and is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) to inventory, organize, preserve, and digitize more than eighty Mazer collections pertaining to lesbian and feminist activism and writings.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9973847813606533
Biography
Francesca Roccaforte was born and raised in New York City, where her early love of photography and aesthetics was nurtured and developed by her parents and environment. Her first solo show was at an organization called the "Door" in the West Village in the 1970s. The "Door" nurtured her creative teenage energy and enabled her to prepare for both intense photographic studies at the School of Visual Arts and Creative Writing at Hunter College in New York. She spent four years immersed in photo studies, and working part time as a documentary photographer, performing arts photographer and darkroom technician. She has taken workshops and classes with W. Eugene Smith, Ansel Adams, Eve Sonneman, Cora Wright Kennedy, Dena, and Alice Beck at the School of Visual Arts.
Roccaforte relocated to the San Francisco area at the age of twenty-three after a photography trip documenting spirituality and religious customs in Italy, Israel and the United States. She was employed in several photography labs and camera stores and completed her visual arts education in California by earning degrees and/or certificates from The California College of Arts, Berkeley City College and Cal State East Bay. Her thesis project, which focused on portraits and accompanying oral herstories of Italian women was both exhibited and published in the 1990s. She has worked as a freelance photographer, worked in educational and medical institutions and assisted with production and operational aspects of film festivals and accompanying events. Currently, she teaches beginning and advanced digital photography to adult learners. She also exhibits her photographic art in the San Francisco Bay Area.
Scope and Content
This collection consists primarily of photographs taken by Francesca Roccaforte. The photographs are assembled from different series and focus on disparate subjects including gay and lesbian pride events, horse racing, cultural events, and self-portraits. Also included in the collection are poems written by Francesca Roccaforte as well as documents related to her professional and academic achievement.
Organization and Arrangement
Materials arranged by type and subject.
Lesbian photographers -- Archives.
- "The Races" photograph series, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Photograph series taken at a horse racing track in 1977 at Belmont Park in New York City, NY. The subjects of the photographs include spectators, jockeys, and horses.
- Assorted photographs, 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  A mix of photographs depicting sporting events, social gatherings, marches, candids, and posed nude portraits.
- Gay Games photographs, 1976-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Photographs from several years of Gay Games. Includes both sporting and social events.
- Assorted series photographs, 1977-1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Various photographs from several different series including: The Water Series 1992, Rocky's Book Series 1976, North Beach Italian 1994, Behind the Door 1994, "Stella" Cafe 1994, 2 Budapest 1988.
- Padua, Italy photographs, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Photographs from a series taken in Padua, Italy.
- Parade photographs, 1978-1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Photographs taken at various gay and lesbian pride events, predominantly in the San Francisco, CA and Oakland, CA areas.
- Parades, landscapes, cultural events, 1978-1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Assorted photographs of gay and lesbian pride parades, landscapes, and various musical or cultural events.
- Professional and academic documents, 1983-1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Contains resumes, certificates, diplomas, and other paperwork related to Roccaforte's academic and professional achievement.
- Self-portraits, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Self-portraits in black and white.
- Poetry, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Various poems written by Francesca Roccaforte.